howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show this is a current episode
currents are shorter and less heavily
produced than our full-length episodes
and generally focus on a single topic as
always links to books articles and
organizations mentioned are available on
the episode page at Jim Wright show.com
that's Jim rut show com today's guest on
this currents episode is Jim Kohn a
professor in the psychology department
the University of Virginia and director
of the Virginia affective neuroscience
laboratory thanks for having me on your
show this is this sounds really fun yeah
thanks for being here it's been been too
long since we chatted indeed to give a
you know sense of some of the things
that Jim works on here's a quote from
his the website of his lab high quality
social relationships correspond with
longer happier and healthier lives facts
that hold true as far as anyone knows
regardless of geography or culture is
that kind of the center of your work yep
we are we are that's that's sort of the
center of gravity around which all my
activities orbit and many of my or my
activities concern the the sort of
neural mechanisms that link social
relationships to enhanced health and
well-being outcomes cool well let's hop
in to is people know who listen to the
podcast regularly in a current episode
we typically start with one item in the
news or tweet somebody made or in this
case a radio appearance Jim made on CBC
radio where he said if the isolation and
I'm presuming that's the isolation in
fact I know from the koban nineteen
pandemic drags on Jim worries we might
be headed for a social recession so over
to you Jim tell us what you meant by
social recession and and this radio
quote was back around the first to April
what is in what is
inspired since that make you think
differently or the same or more compared
to where you were back in April well you
know the social recession is sort of
analogous or may even metaphorical but
but if you think about a financial
recession you're really thinking about a
widespread decrease in access to
financial resources for a period of time
for whatever reason and what I'm worried
about
when I say social recession is is the
widespread decrease in access to social
resources and that concerns me because
social resources are the the human
body's are you know original currency
that makes sense how can we think about
you know what I've read about early
stage people's foragers etc you know
they're essentially their life was
social interactions and in fact one of
my favorite theories about the origins
of language may or may not be true
there's lots of competing theories is
that one of the driving forces for the
evolution of language may well have been
gossip right keeping track of social
status amongst you know a group of
somewhere between 20 and 150 foragers oh
sure
I mean but but it goes deeper than that
so there there are specific functions to
specific kinds of communication all the
way from gossiping at the higher levels
down to finger-pointing at the sort of
lower levels and perhaps more sort of
pleasee amorphic or all evolutionarily
old levels but what really concerns me
is that when you look at the prevailing
theories any of let's say half a dozen
of them you find that most people that
the consensus is sort of pointing us
toward an idea that humans are not bound
to a Pacific terrestrial environment
the way that many so many species are
that we have in fact perhaps due to
pronounced climate variability in our
early
evolutionary development developed to
sort of predominant adaptations one of
them is that we've transcended a
specific terrestrial environment in
favor of any environment like literally
any environment that includes other
humans
so other humans are the ecological niche
that we have adopted as a species in a
process some think like Richard Wrangham
and Brian hare and others includes a
kind of a self domestication like we
domesticated ourselves in order to
become hyper cooperative hyper tolerant
of each other around food sources and
other resource sources and not so
dependent upon a specific kind of
geography or flora or fauna the other
thing that this is resulted in is a kind
of restlessness so one of the reasons
that we populated the globe so rapidly
is that once we developed this once we
transcended specific terrestrial
environments during periods of relative
climate stability we are sort of
standing around tapping our foot going
where's the change where's the change so
we made the change ourselves by moving
our bodies into new places the bottom
line is that our brains and indeed our
bodies right down to the sclera the
whites of our eyes are functionally
adapted to the presence of other humans
they're designed for the presence of
other humans and they don't make sense
if other humans aren't around they don't
they're not useful in any sense you know
it doesn't matter whether we have sclera
around our pupils if there are no other
people around to pay attention to where
our pupils are looking it doesn't help
us with the the terrestrial environment
in any way so we are arguing we have
argued that evolutionarily our brains in
our bodies emerge
you know from the void expecting this
this environment of other humans and
that one of the one of the consequences
of not finding it is that we
automatically mount a stress response
just the same way that a you know that a
salamander might mount a stress response
if it finds itself in a hot dry climate
suddenly because it wants a cold damp
climate and it'll turn right over that
the whole purpose of the stress response
is to get it back to where it's supposed
to be so we know that humans evolved in
a social contacts in fact that people
who listen the show often know that I
will say that cooperation is the human
superpower yeah that allows us to have
penetrated the world and then we'd say
well we're close to chimps but chimps
don't cooperate anywhere near like
humans are close there was something
probably around the development of
language and other things allowed us to
cooperate way more and as you point out
we have physical mechanisms like the
whites of the eyes and many many others
that show that we are deeply social so
presumably your argument about social
recession has something to do with what
happens when the number of social
interactions declines maybe you could go
with that yeah well it but so that gets
us to sort of proximal mechanisms of how
we cooperate and this is where things
get really really weird this is where
things get almost science fictiony for
you and perhaps your listeners and for
me for that matter
because I didn't necessarily expect what
we've wound up finding with these
studies of you know how do you take
social support proximity to a potential
cooperative partner and transform that
into better health and well-being there
are results have surprised us and I'm
gonna explain them to you right now
instead of just going on with this dark
and stormy night introduction the thing
is we're not just autonomous
units deciding to cooperate in a kind of
additive fashion when humans cooperate
we create synergistic effects emergent
properties that transcend the the sort
of additive contributions of our mutual
cooperation and that's really important
because it means that cooperating with
in the with another human in terms of
labor creates multiplicative effects we
actually we actually create exponential
gains economies of scale we say in the
right and in our labs parlance not only
economies of scale in terms of building
model T's but in terms of hunting you
know woolly mammoths and in terms D
indeed of thinking remembering even our
own biographies we create economies of
scale by plugging into social networks
at the conceptual level this is super
interesting because it suggests that we
are capable of sort of connecting up
into units that are qualitatively
different than the individual so group
level units right we create groups that
have a group --is-- ness to them that is
not easily reducible to the individual
units within the group that suggests in
turn that we are it's not it's not just
that cooperation is our super power it's
that cooperation is our lifeblood
cooperation is our hope for survival we
are dependent on cooperation not merely
capable of it and so again you can ask
well what's the evidence for that this
gets into some really strange territory
I've just said that you know when you
know we create these sort of synergistic
or emergent properties when we're
we're inhabiting our groups what is that
result in well as any good behavioral
ecologist will know any critter on earth
and humans or critters pardon me I hope
that's not offensive to anybody
humans are critters who have to manage
resources right so we when we are making
a decision about whether to cooperate or
not or whether to walk up a hill
for example we are simultaneously making
a decision to invest metabolic resources
in that activity and if we're gonna
invest there better be some payoff and
it's not always obvious what that payoff
is but these are the calculations that
we're making all the time and it turns
out just at the behavioral or perceptual
level that if let's go back to the hill
if I'm standing looking at a hill I see
that hill as steeper than it actually is
now that's why land by myself and why do
I do that
because and this is these are all
empirical findings by the way I do that
because my brain is not so subtly trying
to talk me out of walking up the hill
because all else being equal it costs
less in terms of bioenergetic resources
to walk up the hill and do not walk up
the hill right so I see it as steep in
proportion to how much motivation I have
to seek whatever is at the top of the
hill now I put a heavy backpack on you
about 20% of your body weight and guess
what I find the hill becomes even
steeper in your perception you see the
hill as steeper with the heavy backpack
on then you do without it and you see it
is steeper than it actually is
even that at a baseline state now
keeping that heavy backpack on oh by the
way and we do this again I want to
remind everyone because the big reveals
coming up that this is about your brains
management predictive regulation as
Peter sterling calls it and the
neuroscientist predictive regulation of
your body's energetic resources glucose
in the bloodstream
metabolic rate all of these things
when your backpack is on your heavy
backpack is on your bio energetic
resources are more heavily taxed you
have fewer available to you so you see
the hill as steeper and that means that
you're gonna require something even
greater at the top of the hill before
you're going to invest all that
bioenergetic work in climbing up it
here's the big reveal we put your good
friend right next to you you still have
that heavy backpack on but when your
good friend is standing next to you the
hill corrects itself in terms of how you
perceive its steepness it looks less
steep now we've just framed this whole
perceptual finding in terms of the
brain's management of literal
bioenergetic resources how does it take
a friend standing next to you and
translate that into a sort of budget
that it that assumes more bioenergetic
resources we're not gonna eat our friend
probably done most of us not going to do
that most of the time well this is where
we have to talk about how the brain
creates a model of the self and what the
self is and this is some neuro
scientific work that I published back in
initially back in 2013 we have a big
replication coming out with a much
larger more robust and more
representative sample but what we did is
we looked at sort of how the brain made
a model of the self when it was under
threat threat of mild electric shock and
how the brain made a model written sort
of responded when we put a friend under
threat of shock and then how the brain
responded when we put a stranger under
threat of shock and what we found is
that when we put a friend under threat
your brain creates a response and in a
model of self that looks almost
identical to the one it creates when
we put you yourself under threat but
that's not true for a stranger at all
what we find in short is that the self
which is a neural activity that the
brain engage in since it's not a thing
you can't take it out of the head and
weigh it and bounce it like a basketball
the self is an activity we self as a
verb we engage in selfing and as we
construct that self that sense of self
that subjective sense of self that we
use like a like a measuring device to
decide how many resources we have
available to us to engage with the world
we include our social networks in that
calculation we include our social
networks indeed in that representation
of what our self is and contains and
people will if you look in literature
and you know song lyrics from the 1970s
if you look at the way children talk
about themselves we have documented all
of these things in various writings
people will say when they're around
their loved one they feel larger they
feel more powerful they feel taller and
what we're arguing is that the brain is
in fact giving them that literal
perception much the same way that a
friend standing next to you alters your
perception of the steepness of a hill so
extrapolate this out to our fear my fear
at least of social recession when during
the best of times when we're around a
rich social network which I'll will
remind you
we think the brain assumes is going to
be there as it budgets its energetic
resources community in its daily
activities
when under normal circumstances where
we're relatively calm we we tend to
budget more resources toward things like
the immune system growing hair repairing
tissue you know just dealing with our
leaky the the proverbial leaky roofs of
our bodies and thinking about things
like composing operas writing books you
know making art thinking of new ways to
put an addition onto your house instead
of devoting those cognitive resources to
dealing with getting food or avoiding
danger but when we're apart from those
social resources our blood our brains
blood flows more to those regions that
tend to deal with emergencies and we
tend to alter our body's energetic
budget such that we're putting more
glucose into the bloodstream instead of
storing it in glycogen and a you know
leveraging it to repairing body tissue
and boosting our immune system and
that's because we have figured out when
we're alone that we have fewer social
resources to draw from our self has
contracted and we're going to have to
budget accordingly we're going to either
have to do less stuff or we're gonna
have to pay more for whatever we do yeah
it's interesting makes a lot of sense
that when I think about it if we've
evolved as we certainly have in this
deep social interactive network that's
really an extended part of our self and
who we are if we detect that we don't
have those resources it sounds like it
can happen it does happen unconsciously
it's just our perception of where we're
situated instead of being able to apply
our bodily energetics to the normal
housekeeping etc it makes sense that we
into something like a vigilance mode
Here I am you know away from my troupe
of fellow Apes and something is wrong
something is up this is not business as
usual and it would you know make sense
they actually have a separate State for
that kind of situation is that is that
sort of a reasonable way of framing that
I think so
I'm but I would want to keep it focused
as much as we can on the management of
bioenergetic resources because this is
really key what you find when you're
alone what your brain finds and this is
often implicit as you suggest that it's
it's often outside of subjective
awareness your brain just budgets your
body's resources differently right so it
assumes access to fewer resources when
you're by yourself and that means you
have to decide differently about how
what kind of behaviors to engage in
because all behavior is costly right so
if you're gonna go you know up that hill
that steep hill with that heavy backpack
on if you had your friend with you well
then maybe there's a there's a cupcake
at the top and that's sufficient
motivation to go up to the top because
you're friends with you you've got extra
extra energy but if your friends not
with you you're gonna need like 12
cupcakes at the top to motivate you to
walk up that hill okay right so that's
one thing but the other thing is if you
look at it from the other perspective
chances are the number of cupcakes on
the top of the hill hasn't changed so
what does that mean you're just not
going to go up that hill so let's move
out of metaphor zone and back into real
life what does that look like that looks
like lion bed lying around the house not
going out that looks like depression in
fact that is depression when you start
going through long periods of adjusting
to a world in which you have fewer
resources everything that you do
looks like the proverbial steeper Hill
it's hard
to go to the store it's harder to put on
your shoes it's harder to get up out of
bed it's harder to go anywhere do
anything now imagine that you are and I
don't have to imagine this very hard
imagine that you are a young parent
you've got a seven year old and a 9 year
old at home for example as I do and
you've got a home school so you've lost
the social resource of the schools and
and daycare you've got your job you've
got no access or limited access to
friends grandparents babysitters it's
hard for a lot of people to do anything
but sleep yep okay I'm getting it this
is very interesting so let me see if I
can rephrase it just one of things I try
to do on the show quite a bit and then
you tell me whether I'm missing the
essentials or not that we pick up a
implicit signal from our social context
which determines which drives you know
deep level energetic metabolic processes
in our brain such that we have more
glucose in our blood and less if it's
used for bodily restorative things which
changes how our brain slash emotional
states evaluate opportunity versus costs
ah ah the desire or motivation to climb
up the hill to get one cup cake in such
a way that systematically we are in a
state that is not different than being
depressed in fact maybe that is what
being depressed is is that pretty close
to the story and in two sentences that's
the story that's the basic story okay
so will either will either be depressed
and lie around and try not to spend
those metabolic resources so we can
devote as many of them as possible to
keeping you know taking minimal care of
our bodies or we'll mount a full-on
stress response so that we have enough
energy to get out into the world and do
things and we'll
and gate will subject our bodies to what
in our lab we call physiological
weathering where we are constantly you
know on a kind of a slow drip kind of
fashion moving through the world without
sufficiently protecting ourselves from
infection or devoting our our resources
to you know taking care of our bodies so
we by weathering we slowly deteriorate
and that starts affecting our health
this is this is why people under chronic
stress not only can become depressed and
anxious but in fact are likely to get
sick in fact there's there's a finding
you may not know you may know this
because you have an interest in this
area I know but the more socially
isolated you are the more likely you are
to die of anything at all at any time no
matter where you live or what culture
you inhabit it is the most deadly thing
that can happen to you just about except
for maybe a boulder falling on your head
it's a very bad thing to be suddenly
isolated with a little asterisk and that
asterisk is involuntarily there's few
there are a few things more wonderful
and soothing and beautiful than
voluntary isolation when you have the
option to go and reconnect with your
social group whenever you want then
because social groups are also an
investment and then you can you can rest
from that investment but when but when
it's involuntary you are you are screwed
and that's where we're at for sure right
yes what would we expect to see as
implications or ramifications or second
or the next order effects from this
period of involuntary separation from
our social context well I mean one of
the things that I worry most about is
that when you are overtaxed in this way
by in voluntary isolation one of the
region
of the brain that is going to be
fatigued or slowly Minh vested in is
your prefrontal cortex your ability to
think abstractly plan contingencies that
make sense
etc so I mean in effect you get Dumber
right when we should not get Dumber this
is a bad time for all of us to get
Dumber but but that's one of the things
that we can expect from long periods of
social isolation and this is you know
people when they talk about depression
one of the symptoms of depression is
cognitive difficulties problems with
memory and so forth this is the sort of
thing we can expect from social
isolation as well interesting let's move
on from that a little bit that's very
good and very deep very powerful level
of analysis I would I'm curious what you
think about that perhaps a unconscious
rejection of this phenomena of social
isolation and the resultant depression
or quasi depression is what may be
driving this earlier than is probably
good from a public health perspective
reopening you know people have an
absolute live beto to escape this state
of social isolation and if we had add to
it your hypothesis that the prefrontal
cortex functioning has also been reduced
and you know the PFC is extremely
important for planning particularly
things that require multiple steps and
so if the prefrontal cortex functioning
is decreased the ability to make optimal
trade-offs between continuing social
isolation even with some pain and some
negatives and breaking social isolation
so as to relieve yourself of this
low-level aggravating depression and
that may be what's one of the main
driving factors to this
to this perhaps to rapid reopening yeah
I think that's absolutely the case I
think it's absolutely the case and this
is where they're suddenly there's a huge
role for culture in social norms right
because if your culture is one that's
going to emphasize more sort of
pro-social behavior or you have through
whatever media of communication the TV
you know the newspaper the internet just
eat shouting across the street at a
socially distant safe space whether you
know if you if you know that your your
broad social community is also doing
what you're doing then it's gonna be
easier for you to do it because it's
gonna it's gonna encode a little bit of
that I'm part of my group back into your
mind right but if your group is disposed
or your culture is disposed to say
this I don't believe the government you
know if you're more of a sort of
individualistic culture I don't really
like that term but it'll serve for now
like we have in the u.s. I like the old
you know McLuhan you know paranoid
culture I think that was McLuhan then
you're gonna be a lot more agreeable
with just sort of going out and risking
infection or you might not even realize
that you are risking infection you'll
just say oh this is all and
you're gonna have a harder time
resisting that because it's gonna feel
like an opportunity cost to your brain
to stay home and remain isolated so the
more that feels like an I mean that's
this that's you know this is a little
bit of a tangent but that's what the
subjective experience of mental fatigue
literally is mental fatigue is not
literally a decrease in energy in your
brain mental fatigue is the signal that
you get subjectively
from your brain that whatever it is
you're doing
you'd rather be doing something else
that makes a lot of sense let's move on
to a a Cintiq which I'm gonna call zoom
culture yeah we all we all know that
we're doing a lot of people at least are
doing a lot more virtual interaction and
I will say as we talked about in the
pregame talk a little bit you know I'm
busier than I've ever been at least in
the last 19 years since I retired from
my business career and most of that is
on zoom I probably do 20 zooms a week
now up from maybe 10 G's prior to prior
to the pandemic and personally it works
for me I don't find it draining the way
some people report etc and it may just
be my own quirk of quite extroverted
personality but I like zoom culture it's
essentially replaced for me that watch
much of which I gave up that a lot more
phone calls to especially to my closest
friends and my brothers and my cousins
and my nephews and this and that but
again I may well be an outlier I know
that I am in many ways give us your
thoughts from your scientific
perspective of to what degree zoom
culture is a reasonable substitute or a
partial substitute or may actually may
even make things worse I'd love to get
the neuroscience perspective on this
well you know again I I appeal to
resources so how hard is whatever task
you're trying to accomplish on when
you're using zoom versus when you're in
person right and if the the task that
you're trying to accomplish is to
communicate simple messages to hundreds
of people as in you know one of these
big webinars or whatever then clearly
zoom is super easy right and and so it's
gonna be it's gonna feel easier because
it is easier right but if the task is to
understand and implicitly react to
subtle nonverbals as you interact with
your
staff or your boss or you know public
official or whatever it is then zooms
gonna make it harder because zoom is
simply it's like it's like it's like the
mp3 file of communication right it's
just it's just taken out a lot of the
the it's digital it's digital and it's
reduced and compressed digital and we
are designed for analog right and that
analog creates way more information and
our brains are set up to one respond to
that information and to wonder where the
hell that information is if it's not
available
and that wondering that that sort of
wondering creates an extra process that
the brain doesn't want to engage in all
right you don't want to spend more you
always want to spend less so for a lot
of people not you Jim but for a lot of
people zoom communications because they
lack a lot of that essential implicit
information they create an extra
cognitive process that people have to
engage in to try and figure out what
they're communicating and what's being
communicated to them now if you add in
here's a simple way to understand this
add in the little zoom window that shows
you right that reflects you right and
now you've added yet another cognitive
process because you've got a
self-monitoring load that you don't have
under ordinary analog communication
circumstances
this is why I think zoom it's it's
useful for certain kinds of projects and
for me I use it i-i've even found it
helpful in a lot of ways teaching
courses for example now I know all the
names of my students because they're
printed in front of me but over the long
haul
the returns I've said in at least one
interview elsewhere are going to be
diminishing and they're going to be
diminishing and just the kind of
economic curve that that you might think
of when you think of diminishing returns
let me push back on that just a little
bit okay except when watching myself as
I become more of a Zoomer
and just to give you a sense of my own
uses of zoom let's say I do 20 zooms a
week about 15 or one-on-ones
you know communications with people who
reach out to me through having heard my
podcast or active on my Facebook groups
rally point alpha and the game B group
or lots of old friends well you know
just pairwise interactions and and those
are pretty good and then the most
interesting ones are three or four small
group conversations a week somewhere
between 4 and 8 people and those seem to
go well and one a week or maybe two of
these large group webinar things which I
find ok frankly in the same way that
going to scientific big scientific
meetings are just ok right yeah the real
meet at a scientific meeting to me is
the conversation the hallway and having
a beer afterwards rather than the
presentations I find the same fact room
from zoom but here's where I push back a
little bit as I said I've been a Zoomer
now with a significant amount of my
interactions with the world but less
than currently for a couple of years and
I found that I've developed we might
call procedural memories or now unloaded
tasks that help me make zoom better you
mentioned one and when people ask me how
do you use zoom without going insane I
say the first thing is never never look
at that little box with you in it it's
interesting that I discovered more or
less intuitively what you could explain
from a neuro and body energy perspective
which is
looking at your own little box in in
zoom makes you do some processing that's
totally useless and may well be net
negative right yeah we don't have that
experience in the real world
and why the hell would we want to do it
now so so don't do that the other thing
I have noticed particularly in these
small groups which to me are more
difficult to cognitively process than
the pairwise the pairwise I look at is a
much augmented form of a phone call
basically so that is something we're
already know how to do is do long phone
calls with our friends and people that
want to talk to us and this is just a
better way of doing phone calls but the
small group part where you really have
to read body language and whose turn it
is to talk and all those sorts of things
I find that I am now focusing on
people's Bobble emotions way more than I
used to looking at their hands or their
hands calm on their desk or are they are
their hands kind of fidgeting around and
they're spreading and opening their
fingers which I think I'm reading now is
that hey they feel it's their turn to
talk right are they leaning into the
camera and the mic or are they sitting
back with their arms crossed and I
probably wasn't doing that very much or
at least as much on March first as I am
doing now so I think that it is possible
to learn to build unconscious so
therefore relatively unloaded cognitive
processes that allow one to extract a
lot though not all of the cues we get in
let's let's focus particularly on this
small group thing in face to face from
zoom and I'm finding that the small
groups are working better now than they
were three months ago so I think we're
all getting better at it but I will say
that my prediction if I could borrow the
eyes of God for a little while to look
at some of your zoom interactions would
be that you're it's not just you that's
noticing the finger movements and body
postures of your conversation partners
but it's also your conversation partners
who are spending more time noticing
their own body postures in their finger
and and etc and that you know not to get
too fancy but you know anytime you have
a conversation you start you start
especially as the conversation moves on
you start creating a kind of a little
mini dynamical system right and so all
of that gets all that's gonna get and
work its way in the system itself is
going to have a kind of cognitive load
that I I worry about now I could be
wrong I'm totally speculating there and
I would also say that I have found
certain activities to be remarkably
easier with zoom and this is something
that I'm gonna remember as things if
things ever get back to normal so for
example one of the things I spend a lot
of my time doing is editing papers with
grad students and kind of everybody
hates that students hate it I hate it we
passed manuscripts back and forth they
get lost what version is it you know
when we sit together in a room it feels
awkward to sit side-by-side looking at a
screen together but somehow doing a zoom
conversation and sharing the screen and
looking at the document at the same time
it's just magical it's it I I do it
every day now and find it actually
enjoyable whereas before I used to find
it horrible so I don't know I haven't
thought carefully about why that is but
I'll grant you that is one area that
that seems like zoom has made more
efficient and efficiency if I'm right
about all the stuff we've been talking
about today efficiency is the name of
the game that makes well of course a lot
of sense if evolution is what brought us
to where we're at and Oh shocking I
actually believe in evolution unlike
half of Americans then you know
energetics has got to be one of the main
drivers uh you know lower level drivers
of evolution we all know the real payoff
is did you successfully reproduce and
everything else is secondary to that but
energetics has got to be a very big
supporting pylon in that structure let's
move on to our last topic which is a
recent tweet from you a retweet
of New York Times article and I think
this plays into awful lot of what we're
talking about though and it's somewhat
different domain and the title of the
article was expecting students to play
it safe if colleges reopen is a fantasy
and the subtitle of the article was
safety plans border on delusional lead
outbreaks of kovin 19 among students
faculty and staff and this has got to be
pretty important in your life had a you
know major university that either I
don't know what UVA is doing but you
know react to that
oh well geez man I mean look we're all
under all this cognitive load because
we've been socially isolated for months
so under the best circumstances none of
us is doing our best work right now
maybe you are maybe you're doing your
best work I don't want to speak for
everybody but most people are not and
also under the best circumstances people
who are in the developmental phase of
their life that we call late adolescents
are not great decision makers by and
large insurance companies know this very
well that's why and and we don't know
this well enough as a society to keep
people from driving for example until
they're 30
just what I'd like to do not really but
let them vote at 16 but don't let them
drive until they're 30 but the the the
the thing is there's also this
terrifying reality that institutions
like UVA are facing which is just
unfathomable hits in financial resources
I mean that millions of dollars per
semester that translate to support staff
jobs people's livelihoods the ability to
institutionally support research and
teaching I mean it goes on and on to
keep the lights on
and so people responsible for those
kinds of problems are in a state of near
constant panic trying to figure out how
to get the the proverbial lights back on
and so there's an incentive for them not
to think as carefully about the
transmission risk right meanwhile
they're already getting a little bit
dumber if I'm right and certainly the
kids are getting dumber and so we're all
sort of going yeah sure sure these
college students can come back and
monitor their own health behavior well
enough and so forth just as well as they
can keep each other from getting
pregnant and from crashing cars drinking
too much on Saturday night yeah yeah now
I could be giving them too little credit
maybe I am but I don't think I am and
also when I factor in the the the sort
of the incentive that the power
structure in the administration here and
elsewhere has to you know there are
financial commitments to reopen then it
seems to me like it's it's just there's
a lot of pressure to make the wrong
decision here and I think it's going to
it there's also a lot of pressure to
discount the cost of those decisions for
populations outside the student
population not just faculty but you know
custodial staff the local community that
has nothing to do with the university
many of whom are highly vulnerable aging
or african-american where these are
groups that we know are at higher risk
so you know we're not just playing with
undergraduate lives here or
undergraduate in fact infection rates so
that's that's my soapbox yep and that
you know I think you hit it exactly on
the head that we're at
addled state we have crushing financial
imperatives not just for institutions
like the University of Virginia but for
every working person and then we have
the moral social network effects right
it's you know truthfully if one were an
Randian a crazed individualist you could
say we need to take the risk and reward
for ourselves but on but that is not
true as you point out we're all
connected on a social network and
someone who decides to expose themselves
to more risk is actually increasing the
risk for lots of people around them many
people who they don't even know in the
second and third-order social network
that's right we got ourselves quite a
conundrum here we're not gonna try to
solve it today and I want to thank you
Jim for an extraordinarily interesting
deep and perceptive conversation thank
you Jim I had a great time yeah I really
was it was good production services and
audio editing by Jared Jane's consulting
music by Tom Muller at modern space
music com
[Music]